do
[Music]
hello hello everybody welcome to the
92nd live episode of ask a widget
uh i hope you're all doing well and as
you know today is a live video chat
session
so i will be sharing the link very soon
before i do that let me just
uh
remind you all just in case that i have
created a new short clips channel in
which you will in which all the new
short clips will be going
so the link for that is in the
description this is also you can see it
on the screen youtube.com slash object
chopped clips
okay so uh with that said let me share
the link
for joining the video chat
uh and before i do that again
there are very simple rules
one question per person please the topic
must be the russia ukraine geopolitics
and please keep your question short and
precise
and
let me share
the link
should be able to see it now
let's do it let me pin it up
yes it is pinned now so
so you should be able to see that
so i'll wait for the people to join and
today i'm going to make one small change
so i will take the question
and then after i take the question i
will be the only person on the screen
that that way i think we will be able to
keep things moving
faster
than
in in previous episodes
so i can see people joining now
so let's uh get get somebody in
i think people are still settling down
so let's bring in mr uh
other
so i can see people joining now so
so let's uh
get somebody uh can you please uh
let me put that whatever it is
so let's bring in mr uh
oh so i saw
[Music]
so i am from kanpur
and what's your name
is it
yes sir
yes regarding uh which is not uh
directly linked to ukraine and uh russia
conflict
the topic is the
russia ukraine conflict
[Music]
since many days but you have never
picked one
that why india doesn't invest 25 to 30
billion dollars per year on research
especially in military research work
yeah okay okay let me answer it in brief
uh i think india should spend more in
research and development yeah
and so thanks nice to meet you
thank you nice to meet you let's bring
in somebody else and please keep the
topic of your question
related to the subject at hand all right
that's my request
uh let's bring in mr himanshu
hello
hello hello sir
hi where are you from sir
i'm from
jaipur rajasthan
nice to meet you sir what's your
question
so my question is uh
regarding the news that is being
shown and for this russia and ukraine
conflict like for example uh
the crimea which was annexed by russia
in 2014
uh is dependent on ukraine for water
supplies
but ukraine has stopped with water
supply but uh and this all this is also
a reason uh to provoke
russia can be provoked with this as
there is no water supply in ukraine uh
crimea
but this news is nowhere in this
media and
i don't know how much they can they
control the media
and
even in indian media also
so
so what's the question basically
question is
who controls indian media majorly even
they do not show these types of news
and not a single point from the russia
side
okay i get it good question sir i'm
gonna put you off the screen now okay so
thank you and very good question
uh
so the question is why who controls the
indian media that is the question and
why is none of this being reported in
the indian media and in the world media
so it's it's true what himanshu just
said is absolutely right
what's happened since 2014 after the
russian annexation of the crimea
peninsula what's happened is that the
ukrainians have stopped the uh there was
a i think there was a river or a big
canal that used to supply water to the
crimean peninsula from ukraine and the
ukraines cut that off uh that supply off
they built a dam
to uh
prevent this water going into the
crimean peninsula and that essentially
dried out the entire thing
and uh the western media has never
reported this and neither has the indian
media
so that's what we are seeing all the
time that the reporting that is
happening in the media whether it's the
western media or the indian media it is
not free and fair it is not unbel it is
not balanced it is not objective it's
not accurate they are only showing some
a certain side of the story
and that brings us to the question which
himanshu asked that who controls the
media who controls the indian media who
controls the western media
now in the case of the western media
let's say the bbc or the or cnn or
washington post or new york times or
whatever it is the guardian
they are all controlled they essentially
act as propaganda arms of their
governments that's what it is
and of course there is funding that
comes in from china as well so they are
very much pro-china as well so to
understand who controls the media you
have to look into who is funding who
owns these media companies
who are the shareholders and all that if
you look into that just follow the money
and then you will understand
why
the news coverage is the way it is now
in the case of the indian media i have
said this yesterday as well last week
also
that there are two three channels in
india indian media channels that are
covering the ukraine conflict
and they're covering it from the nato
perspective or the u.s perspective
i i don't mean to say that they should
cover it from a russian perspective i
mean to say that they should cover it
from an indian perspective what is the
indian national interest in all of this
right what's best for india they don't
tell you that they simply tell you the
u.s perspective of the nato perspective
so the reporting even in the india
indian media is not fair it's not
balanced it's not objective
so and and i i don't know who's i mean i
have not done the investigation myself
as to who controls them who is funding
them who owns them i'm sure all of you
can do it i'm sure most of the
information is available somewhere or
the other in the public domain
so just follow the money and you will
get your answer
right but it's clear that the reporting
is not fair it's not balanced it's not
objective and
it's it's uh
not in line with the indian national
interest
so that's what i can say himanshuji uh
thank you very much very good question
nice meeting you
all right
uh let's bring in somebody else
let's bring in a
i'm not sure what his name is hello
hello sir hello
hi what's your name sir where are you
from
maharashtra nice
nice to meet you sir what's your
question
so my question is in the russia ukraine
conflict can india lead an alliance like
g7 bri nato to
to carry on negotiations with any
country which are responsible or war
countries
which are fought fighting with each
other
and take decisions on world affairs and
atc things
by forming an organization like this big
organizations
okay good question sir uh i will answer
it i'm gonna
uh remove you from the screen while
answering so the question uh he has
asked is should or can india form a
multi-national
organization that does negotiations
and solves geopolitical issues and
conflicts and all that the question is
i'm sure india can do it
the question the real question is what
does india gain from that
if you
see from at the international level
whatever you do should be from the
perspective of your own national
interest now let's say you want to play
a big shot and you want to go and
negotiate and solve conflicts and solve
problems and all the question is you're
going to spend a lot of time and effort
maybe money doing all this
what do you get in return from for this
right and if you go and negotiate and
try to solve problems will people listen
to you so these are the questions these
are practical questions you have to ask
yourself
we have a limited diplomatic core our
government has limited time and money
and all that
and the only sole objective of the
government
is to
further india's national interest now if
you have x amount of hours per year and
x amount of money per year
to do this would you like to spend some
of that time and money
solving the world's problems when your
job is to solve the problems of the
country so that's the uh that's the
question we have to ask ourselves and
that's why it's not practical
for india to go and go around solving
the world's problems creating an
alliance or organization and all that
unless
it actually benefits india
so it's a question of being absolutely
practical
so i'm sure india can do it but question
is what does india gain
in return
so uh as of now there's uh
as we as we know there are some
negotiations happening in ukraine uh
i think today
the israeli prime minister went to
ukraine
or
he i think he went to moscow and he and
he spoke
and he spoke with uh
with with president putin
and he's trying to
try to trying to negotiate some sort of
agreement or some sort of thing like
that
because there are lots of jewish people
who live in ukraine and lots of jewish
people who live in
in the u in in russia as well i think at
least 20 percent
of israel's population
is
can speak russian so that's why that
country israel has a clear uh is is a is
in a way a stakeholder in what's
happening there so as long as there is
some
national interest something that
furthers your national interest there's
no point doing this so that's what i can
say
so yeah a good question
and let's bring in somebody else let's
bring in uh
shikhar saraf
hello hello hello sir good evening
good evening sir good evening sir where
are you from
could you could you mute that
from
so my question is that why are the
ukrainian officials
uh cons
repeatedly other than any leader
insisting pm modi to convince russia to
stop the invasion
or could you repeat that could you
repeat that please i didn't get it
sir why are the ukrainian officials
repeatedly insisting pm modi other than
any leader
to convince russia to stop the invasion
okay oh i got it okay
yeah okay because it's echoing all the
time so
uh the question is why are the ukrainian
leaders insisting
that pian modi should
resolve the problem and negotiate or
something uh as far as i know i have not
heard any ukrainian
leader politician
etc insist that prime minister modi
should go and negotiate and resolve the
problem
i have not heard any such news
what's happening what we are seeing is
that
the western nations the english-speaking
nations especially the us
and
the uk
and various other countries essentially
the nato countries there
uh they are they have launched a kind
kind of a campaign on social media in
which they are blaming india for
abstaining
in the u.n security council votes
against russia so they insist that india
needs to india should have
voted against russia and that's a huge
stain on india's character apparently so
india is now no longer a democracy in
india supports fascism and evil and
violence and all that even though china
has done the same thing and they're not
speaking a word against china so that's
what's happening uh the ukrainians have
not been interesting that
that our prime minister
pm modi should get involved in this as
far as i've heard i've not heard
anything and i have been following this
quite uh
quite intently what's happening
so shikhar good question that's that's
what i can tell you all right thank you
uh good question nice meeting you
okay let's bring in
uh whom shall i bring in
let's bring in mr shrey
hello
can you hear my voice
okay okay great yes sir what's your
question
my question is
even though countries like kazakhstan
is separated from soviet union but still
most of them are i mean they are still
supporting russia even my friend visited
this country he said that people still
prefer russia over many other may
compare to western why is it that
they're still supportive of russia and
a good question nice meeting you i'm
gonna answer it now
so uh what shrey said is why are these
republics the former ussr republicans
who are now no longer part of that
country like tajikistan kazakhstan
uzbekistan azerbaijan etc why do they
still support
russia and in in
geopolitical matters in things like the
ukraine conflict etc why do they support
the russians
that's a very good question so there are
multiple reasons for that first of all
they are still very much under the
russian sphere of influence
russia is a very powerful nation
and even though these countries are now
no longer part of
no longer part of the ussr the uss are
broke up and but yet they are still very
much part of the
russian sphere of influence so the
russians
can influence matters within these
countries
and of course there is the military
angle as well russia can project
military power anytime it lacks in these
countries
and also the economies are still to uh
to a significant extent quite integrated
and many of these leaders
uh owe a lot to to to russia
for for the power that they hold some of
them you could consider them you know to
be in a way puppet regimes
of russia the same way nato has a number
of puppet regimes in various other
various countries in a similar way the
russians also do that
so there are multiple reasons why these
countries
always support russia first of all
they are kind of scared of russia the
russians
the russians can
can intervene militarily if they like if
these countries go against russia the
russians will not tolerate these
countries going hand in hand with with
america or nato or anything like that so
these are the reasons you know it's at
the end of the day it's all about hard
power russia has the hard power to keep
these countries in line
so that's why countries like uzbekistan
etc uh
they still tow the russian line they
still have most of these countries they
still have russia as the official
language there are lots of
the economies are integrated towards to
a large extent and there are very deep
relations with moscow so these are
multiple reasons and of course if you
look at the people there are lots of
people to people contacts and the people
still i believe would be nostalgic about
the way the ussr used to be because i am
sure there was more order and more uh
efficiency to some extent under the
during the ussr days compared to how
things are being run lighter right now
so these there are multiple reasons why
this attitude is prevalent that the
people
still support russia and even the
governments
still
support russia so that's an interesting
question
has asked thank you very much
uh let us bring in
whom shall we bring in let's bring in mr
mr raj
okay great uh what's your
so question sir
is uh what exactly happened in 97 1971
when india and pakistan went on a war
and the western countries and china came
with pakistan and russia came with india
and is that the reason why india and
russia has a really good relationship
good question
good question raj thank you for the
question and nice meeting you i'm gonna
now answer the question
so the question is very interesting it's
about 1971 but it's about geopolitics
it's about india russia relations so
it's a good question
so what happened in 1971 is that the
pakistanis launched an unprovoked attack
on india
and india had to retaliate the attack
was launched there were these air raids
from east pakistan which was then is
pakistan it's not bangladesh
so india had to retaliate and the two
countries went to war
and the entire western bloc
the americans and of course those days
the chinese were
the chinese were becoming close to the
americans so all these countries
what they did was they opposed india
and the americans even sent an aircraft
carrier into the bay of bengal to
intimidate india and prevent india from
doing any significant damage to east
pakistan and what the americans found
when they came to the bay of bengal is
that there were soviet nuclear
submarines waiting for them in the bay
of bengal and that's why they were not
able to
go ahead
the uss enterprise i believe it was the
aircraft carrier it was not able to go
and threaten india and that's why india
was able to because of this support from
the ussr india was able to go ahead and
dismember pakistan and and free and
liberate bangladesh from the horrible
genocide that the people of bangladesh
were suffering mainly the bangladeshi
hindus
so the americans what they wanted what
they were doing is they were supporting
the genocide of the of the bangladesh
bangladesh people they were supporting
pakistan in what pakistan was doing
and they they lecture us about human
rights and on that today right so they
were trying to prevent india from
pursuing its national interest they were
trying to support pakistan they were
trying to support the pakistani genocide
in bangladesh and it is the ussr
that stepped in that intervened and
prevented america from stopping india
from doing its military action
so why did the russians why did the ussr
do that because they needed india
on their side it's a geopolitical game
it's not because we are friends and we
love each other it's because it was in
their national interest
to
to ensure that the american
scheme
was defeated the american scheme was to
encircle india from two sides east
pakistan and west pakistan and the
pakistanis were
the where america's clients stayed
and that's why it was good for them
because india had already aligned with
the ussr india was officially a member
of the nam the non-aligned movement but
it was de facto was a satellite state
you could say of the ussr
so the americans were very concerned
about that and that's why they were
using pakistan to counter balance india
and china as well so all of these
countries were against india the ussr
came to india's rescue and india was
able to break up pakistan and liberate
bangladesh so it was not out of love for
india or because they they were friends
with india but because they needed this
to happen from their own national
interest perspective
so because india had aligned with the
ussr that's why the two interests were
converging there they were aligned and
that's why they helped india at the time
and uh
so so that's what happened then and
today the situation is different
russia is no longer as powerful as the
ussr used to be it's no longer a genuine
superpower it's a it's the
it's maybe the second most powerful
military nation in the world they have
the world's largest nuclear arsenal
so it is beneficial for india to have a
country like that on our side
so that's the situation that we are
watching that we are in today
uh it is no longer in a position to help
india if there is a conflict with any
other country either pakistan or china
but still it is a great counterbalance
against various countries that are not
really very friendly towards india
the chinese today are obviously
india's biggest adversary on in the
eurasian
theater
and there are other countries also that
are not quite
friendly towards india they don't really
wish us very well
even though they may be in various kinds
of
reasonably good relations relationships
with us so we need the russians to
counter balance all that and that's why
um
so that is the situation which which we
are in today which is very different
from the 19th 1971 situation so that's
the kind of brief
historical background that i can offer
you so raj thank you very much very good
question sir nice meeting you
okay let us bring in mr rishikesh
hello
hello sir nice to see you sir
nice to see you sir where are you from
i'm from hublisa karnataka
great great what's your question
so my question is that russia is
does not have any hatred to civilians
but it uh it also mentioned that it
would use the precision guided
weapons but in the mst report it is said
that they are using 9m79 tok tochka
ballastic missiles and how hazardous it
might be as the nostradamus predicted
that uh zappo is a nuclear power plant
leaks if therefore is our nuclear power
pancreas
okay okay very good question sir thank
you for the question i'm gonna uh answer
it now
so
amnesty international is reporting that
the russians are not doing what they
should be doing
uh russia should be using extremely
precise weapons in order to carry out
its in order to
proceed with the military campaign and
apparently they are not doing that they
are using other weapons as well so
amnesty international supposedly is
saying this
the question is
the question is what is the credibility
of amnesty international amnesty
international is nothing but a
propaganda organization
amnesty international has been bashing
india for decades
right and they are essentially one of
the various
arms
of the u.s that comes into your country
and meddles in your internal affairs and
refuses and issues various kinds of
certificates to you so that's what
amnesty international does i don't know
i have not seen this report that that
they have put out apparently that the
russians are using this missile of that
missile the thing is this
amnesty international has zero
credibility so we don't even need to
talk about them that we don't need to
listen to them we don't need to believe
them they are simply a propaganda arm of
the united states and and of the west
i'm not saying it's a bad thing but we
know the track record in india they are
very much anti india and therefore we
know that
none of what they say is factual
so this is simply
one of the ways of continuing the
propaganda war against russia now what
we know about
how the russian military campaign is
proceeding is that they are trying their
best
to minimize
damage to
ukrainian infrastructure and they are
trying their best not to harm civilians
right so they they in the initial hours
of the of the military campaign they
they hit various military installations
in ukraine using uh
using cruise missiles and those cruise
missile strikes were very accurate
within two three hours the entire
ukrainian air force was grounded right
the russians had complete air
superiority and after that they have
been proceeding very slowly very
carefully
very circumspect they are doing their
best not to
not to even break the traffic rules in
ukraine that's how they are proceeding
and now like a couple of days ago this
story came out there was this a fire
fight at the
i forget the name the nuclear power
plant that rishikesh mentioned there was
a far there was a firefight there what
has emerged
is that the
ukrainians started the fire fight were
firing rocket propelled grenades from
within the compound of the nuclear power
plant and the russians were forced to
retaliate and yet we know that there has
been no significant damage to the power
plant or to the nuclear reactor so the
nuclear reactor is safe
and the ukrainians did this in order to
make it look like the russians have gone
crazy and they're trying to blow up a
nuclear power plant so the
attempt that is repeatedly being
witnessed
there they are the the west is
attempting to show mr putin as a madman
as somebody who has lost all control of
what he is doing is trying to blow up
nuclear power plants nuclear reactors
and he's gone crazy the thing is this if
you want
if you if you want to destroy somebody
you have to first give a justification
for that you have to first
show or portray them as mad if you
portray somebody as is
insane
then it's okay to do whatever you want
with them like in the middle ages in
europe if you wanted to to destroy the
life of of
of a woman
you would all you would have to say is
that she's a witch
she's practicing witchcraft or she's
practicing devil worship once you say
that then you can do anything to her so
that's the kind of thing that used to be
there and today they are using similar
tactics against mr putin they're trying
to portray him as somebody who's gone
mad which is not the case so that is the
information warfare
that we are witnessing information
has been weaponized social media has
been weaponized this is propaganda at a
whole different level so so
i think he's gone now okay very good and
anyway very good question
uh let us bring in
whom shall i bring in let's bring in mr
somia
hello
hi there
hi
yes sir where are you from sir um i'm
from kolkata
kolkata all right what's your question
sir
uh my question is it's a very simple
question
could you tell me
any rational news channel where we can
watch
this what what is happening now
so
we can track uh
the uh
true picture of this conflict russian
ukraine
very good question all right thank you
for the question um so what swamiji has
said is
any good news channel
i don't know any good news channel
that's not the way i gather my news and
information what i do is i don't watch
the news at all i don't watch bbc cnn al
jazeera or rt or whatever it is or any
indian news channel i don't watch the
news at all i get gather my information
from online sources
i don't watch i don't do that all day
but if you do it from a variety of
sources then you will get a good
balanced picture because you know that
when you see this when you look at the
news from the cnn feed it will have a
western flavor if you look at new york
times washington post if you look at the
bbc if you look at the guardian you will
see news that is biased in a certain way
if you look at
let's say indian
news outlets they will have a different
kind of bias if you look at the russian
kind of bias if you look at the chinese
outlet
news outlet media outlet they will have
a chinese
slant or bias and if you go on twitter
you will have lots of impartial
people as well
putting out all kinds of opinions so if
you do that
then you will get a whole
well-rounded perspective and then you
need to use your own judgment
to come to the conclusions as to what is
really happening so that is how i do it
i don't have any one source that i go to
i don't trust any one source i look at
lots of different sources and then i
make my own judgments as to what's
really happening and of course it helps
if you know history then it's not easy
for them for people to fool you
so that's what i do that's the
philosophy i use maybe you all can also
do it and swamiji thank you very much
for the question it's a very interesting
question thank you
okay let's bring in somebody else people
are waving their hands everybody is
waiting let's bring in mr ishwara
hello hi
hi where are you from sir
i'm from bangalore nice to meet you sir
what's your question
i'm an audible sir
yes yes i can hear you
yeah uh from past 100 years there's a
concept of neutral countries like
switzerland island finland austria and
etcetera have their status or their
neutrality faded away in this current
situation
and uh does putin want
ukraine to be the next finland
okay very good question ishwaraji thank
you very much let me answer that
so what ishwar said is that there are a
number of countries that have typically
historically over the past hundred or so
years been neutral
let's take the example of switzerland so
switzerland is famous for its neutral
status right they don't participate in
any war they don't get involved in
politics
and so on and so forth they are neutral
that's what we see them as switzerland
is a neutral country and some other
countries also have
similar statuses
now let's look at why a country like
switzerland would do that switzerland is
a very small tiny country right
a small country like that is easy
it's an easy target for any big country
if they want to come and capture that
country and take away all the resources
so
switzerland says we are neutral we will
not
participate in any conflict any
political thing any geopolitical matter
will stay out of all of this
and
they also the swiss they also provide a
very valuable service
you know what the service is
they are the world's bankers they have
the very famous swiss banks where people
deposit their savings
and uh the thing about the swiss banks
it used to be this way that they would
never ask you any questions as to where
you got the money from how did you
acquire the money they will not ask you
you can go there and in perfect
anonymity stash your cash
so what happened is that sudden became
the favorite place for all kinds of
corrupt politicians and criminals and
smugglers and all that to go and dump
their money and they knew that it will
remain safe in switzerland
we also know
that lots of nazi
treasure was stashed away in switzerland
in these in these swiss banks and many
of these nazis did not ever
get a chance
to go back
and reclaim the money because they would
have got killed in the second world war
and so on
so that's this service that's
switzerland provided to various nations
all across the world and that's why it
was valuable as
a country that remained independent so
it's not
the swiss were not able to remain
independent because they were neutral
they were able to remain independent and
untouched by everybody because they
provided a very valuable service to
everyone
right
so uh switzerland is not actually
neutral they they are they are looking
out for their own self-interest it's a
very small country it's easy for any
country to come and gobble it up right
and they don't even have a standing army
they have this compulsory military
service that every
adult male has to undergo and all adult
males i believe who are
who are physically fit et cetera they
are issued a weapon that they can use
when required and so on so forth
so
so that's the strange concept of
neutrality
and other countries also have tried such
things
and then we also had the so-called
non-aligned movement which never got
anybody anywhere so that's the kind of
information i can offer
about neutral countries with the example
of sudaran
the other question was does mr putin
want to
finlandize ukraine i don't think he
wants to finlandize ukraine he wants to
effect a regime change and
install a new government that is pro
russia
and maybe even take up take out parts of
ukraine which are russian majority
and
integrate them into russia
so that is what i can
say so very good question ishwar thank
you very much
okay
let's bring in
sunil surana
hello
yeah
so my question is uh some countries
despite being obvious enemies for
example india pakistan india china
still they carry on trade between them
uh so like why so
i'm not sure if it's a valid question
but
it's a valid question yeah sure it's
it's a geopolitical question so i'll
take it all right so thank you very much
so why do countries that are that have
a conflicted relationship an adversarial
relationship maybe countries that have
gone to war with each other why do they
still
engage in mutual trade let's say that's
an interesting thing about the world so
it's a good question for instance india
and china everyone knows these are
adversarial countries they have an
adversarial relationship the chinese
occupy parts of our territory illegally
we have gone to war
three times with china 1962 we lost to
china they took away exciting and some
other parts of our territory 1967
they again attacked us india defeated
china in the 1967 war which your history
textbooks will not teach you and in 19
in
1980s also i think it was 88 there was
another another clash which india won
so we have a very
bad relationship with china they lay
claim on our territory even today
arunachal pradesh and so on so forth
more of it and still we have a
significant amount of trade with china
so why is that so because trade is
separate from from warfare you can
weaponize trade also but there are
things in india that the chinese
would like
the chinese use india for raw materials
and then they send you send back to
india their finished products and
because of this because raw materials
are cheaper and finished products are
more expensive that's why they are
enjoying this big trade
surplus with india
and so the trade surplus i don't
remember what the exact figure is it
used to be a few years ago a few years
ago it was about 90 billion dollars
or so maybe it is less now maybe 30 or
50 or something
billion dollars per year so that's a
significant trade surplus they're
enjoying
and
india also wants to continue the trade
so so it's all about mutual benefit
we need something from them they need
something from us so as long as we are
not at war we will continue trade and we
will uh grow our economy in whatever way
we can
so
that's how it typically goes countries
that
our enemies still trade india and
pakistan also trade right a few years
ago india had given the most favored
nation status to the pakistanis
even the u.s and ussr used to have trade
during the cold war days
so
that's how it typically is even when you
are enemies you still want to make money
you still want to benefit as much as you
can
even from your enemy that's how it goes
so that's just the way of the world and
as long as there is no hostility going
on right now we will trade
and we'll make money as as far as there
is mutual benefit so that that's the way
it's always been historically also in
the past
all right sunil so thank you very much
for the question
all right thank you thank you for the
question
nice meeting you bye
okay let's bring in somebody else let's
bring in mr ashu
hello
namaste
nice to meet you sir what's your
question
so my question is sir russia is now
threatening or warning uh sweden and
finland both these countries
also want to join natto and already are
part of eu
so so my question is should they join
nato for their defense or they should
remain neutral or maybe more inclined
towards russia
because of what happening with ukraine
or is it a matter of concern for russia
very good very short very crisp question
appreciate it thank you very much i'm
gonna answer it now so what ashu said is
that russia is threatening various
countries finland
uh and the other country that they
mentioned
poland i suppose so there are see it's
like this there used to be a warsaw pact
the warsaw pact was an anti-anti-nato
alliance of the soviet bloc so i think a
number of countries were part of the
warsaw back poland was the ussr
obviously was there
poland
albania
czechoslovakia czechoslovakia romania
and various other countries i think
there were seven eight countries in that
so this was called the soviet bloc of
countries in eastern europe so that's
where the ussr
uh had its uh
the its its fear of influence now after
the ussr broke up
the russia the russians russia was the
biggest
nation that came out of it and
they were given this assurance in 1991
by the us that nato will not expand even
one inch eastwards and and the americans
have broken that promise almost
immediately in the in 1999 a number of
countries came into nato and they've
been expanding steadily eastwards ever
since
and eventually it became a
matter of life and death life or death
for for russia and that's why we have
the ukraine conflict going on now
so
what we are seeing is that finland
seeks to join nato ukraine also seeks to
join nato and various other countries
also seek to join nato
and
that's why is it so because nato is
right now more powerful
if russia was as powerful as the ussr
they would not dare to express
the thought that we want to join nato
so it's that's how it works in the world
whoever is more powerful you want to be
on the good side
so right now
right now what we are finding what we
are seeing is that the chinese power is
growing and the russian power is already
there it's constant and because china
and russia are working together the
overall power of the of the eastern bloc
the china-russia bloc is growing it's
expanding
and therefore
uh because the
the russians are funded by china they
have the guarantee that the chinese will
support them that's why they are not
really very badly affected by whatever
sanctions are coming their way obviously
there will be some a significant effect
even then
but they have the the backing of the
chinese so now
russia is no longer a waning power it
may be perhaps
a strong enough power that can threaten
various nato countries and we have seen
what they what they've been able to do
in ukraine so now the status is
different
earlier nato was all powerful the us was
all powerful russia was a broken country
now the russian power power seems to be
growing again
and the question every country needs to
ask itself
is
will america be able to save them if
something goes wrong
right
so if they apply to join nato the
process will take some time in the
meanwhile the russians will not like it
and they may come and invade you as well
will the americans be able to save you
they were not able to save ukraine right
so that's the question every country
needs to ask so it's all about
who is more powerful
everybody wants to be on the good side
of whoever is more powerful and that's
why nato was expanding all the time but
now it's very clearly visible that the
americans their power now has limits
earlier they their their power had no
limits all across the
all across the planet
but now we are seeing that their power
is waning they have they have been
forced to withdraw from afghanistan
they've left this big power vacuum in
central asia
and now you can see they've they've lost
ukraine as well so it is visible their
decline is now visible
and obviously there will be
repercussions to that they will not give
up so easily
and the conflict could be in europe
the the fight for for supremacy which
country will come on whose side
so the smaller countries will get caught
in that unfortunately it looks like that
so that's what i can say i cannot make a
prediction as to what will happen will
finland join nato or not if they try to
join nato they may face some serious
consequences from the russians maybe
maybe not depending on the calculations
of how far mr putin thinks he can go at
this point in time maybe five years in
the future he may have a different kind
of plan so that's where we are right now
it's an interesting situation we are now
living in interesting times very
interesting times and the world is going
to change very rapidly in the coming
decade
so very interesting question ashu thank
you for asking the question nice meeting
you
okay
whom shall we shall we bring in okay mr
bhano is back
let's bring in mr banner
hello
good evening sir
good evening good evening you're from
jammu right
yes sir
okay great what's the question so one of
the articles of nato states that you
cannot invade a country but if a small
part of country wants to become
independent or are not treated properly
then the neighboring country may help
them
russia has done the same and u.s has
been doing it
in the various parts of the world like
vietnam afghanistan and many more
so can india invade balochistan using
this article and should india really
invade balochistan
very good question banu thank you for
the question i'll answer it now
so the
so banu mentioned some article in the
nato charter which says that the country
can do so and so things see nato doesn't
get to set the rules in the world
right
nato is an is an alliance of a certain
number of countries and these rules
apply to those countries only
right so we cannot say cite a certain
nato article and say that we can start
doing things according to that
because the article the charter or
whatever it is it applies only to the
member nations and even if they say that
these things are allowed it doesn't mean
that they can impose that rule or the
charter all over the world right they
talk about a rules-based order but they
break the rules all the time they can
set the rules anytime they want they can
break the rules anytime they want so
it's so what can india do what can india
not do it all depends on how strong
india is and that's all it is
right
what a country can do
depends on the country's overall power
and standing and stature on the
geopolitical global
arena
if you are strong enough powerful enough
you can do anything you wish if you are
not strong if you're not powerful then
you can do nothing people will even come
and tell you what to do internally in
your own country
so
if india wants to free balochistan it
doesn't need to cite
an article
in the nato charter if india is strong
enough it can go and go ahead and do
that tomorrow
right now india is not powerful enough
to do such a thing without facing
adverse consequences
so that's what i can say
right so the nato charter or article has
no relevance
to india to asia or to any other country
it all depends on how strong you are the
chinese for instance they they have
broken the agreement they had with the
uk
that hong kong would be under one
country two two systems they broke the
agreement they broke the
uh the treaty they had similarly
similarly the americans broke the iran
nuclear deal it was a treaty they had
signed and they just walked away from it
unilaterally so if you are strong enough
you can do it we know that americans
have intervened militarily in various
countries they've invaded afghanistan
iraq twice
libya so if you are strong enough you
can do it you don't need to cite
anything you could do it because you can
all right banu uh good question and nice
seeing you guys see you again
all right let us bring in somebody who's
been waiting for a while uh let's bring
in abbay
hello
hello sir thank you so much for taking
me uh are we here from bhopal here
my question was
thank you thank you sir my question was
related to uh that when we are negative
on the side of geopolitics today
and now like usa is anti-russia for sure
and with sanctions on russia certainly
it is going to be a sanction or economic
struggle
that is being provided to china as well
so is it is a good situation for us as
well to be emerged as a superpower
economically as well
while the usa we have got the stealth of
usa at the same point of time
and now the sanctions are going to also
impact pakistan
and
china as well along with russia
okay good question thank you for the
question i will answer it now so um
the question is is this the right time
for india to emerge as an economic
superpower
so
what is the definition of an economic
superpower the definition of an economic
support power is a country that has its
economic systems
accepted all around the world for
instance the entire
economic
all the institutions etc economic
institutions are controlled by the us
the world bank the imf imf etc and the
us dollar is the reserve currency that's
accepted all across the world so that's
why the us is an economic superpower now
for india to become
an economic superpower firstly
our economy will have to triple at least
right now our economy is about three
trillion dollars worth right gdp it
needs to become at least 10 trillion
dollars
of gdp for us to be even considered to
be a major economic power so that's a
long way away even if there are
sanctions on russia and it will affect
china badly or pakistan badly it doesn't
mean it's going to be great for us we
are still uh dealing with the kovid
recession which has dragged us down in
the last two three years
and
india needs to if india wants to grow
to the status of 10 trillion dollars of
gdp it's going to be a long hole ahead
of us so you can't become an economic
superpower overnight the sanctions will
will affect russia
but it may benefit china because the
russians are now driven into the chinese
arms so it's a very complicated
situation the sanctions may affect
pakistan but depending on how the
russians deal with iran pakistan may
again come into
the good side of the u.s
for instance if the russians and the
chinese are cooperating financially
economically and militarily with iran
then the americans will again look at
pakistan as a way of counter balancing
iran
even if it affects india badly
right so in that case they may again go
and whoop wu the
pakistanis they may be able to give more
money to the pakistanis than the chinese
can in that case pakistan again becomes
a good
a good dogee
of the americans
right so the situation is right now very
very uh complex it's very it's changing
very fast and india is not in a position
to call itself
an economic superpower anytime in the
near future it will take at least 10
years most likely 20 years
if you are to be more realistic to reach
the 10 trillion
mark
when it when we are there then we may be
a major power economically and not yet a
superpower
we have to reach the 15 trillion
trillion dollar mark to be a real
superpower but it
it can be considered to be super power
only if you have a similar military
strength so the situation is very
complex just because there are sanctions
right now doesn't mean that we are now
in one or two years gonna be a
superpower no no it's very much
very difficult it's a it's a difficult
road ahead and there are lots of
struggles we are going to face
uh because the americans are sanctioning
russia it doesn't mean that they are our
good friends they are threatened
threatening to sanction india as well
the katsa sanctions
is something that they are considering
right now because india is purchasing
the s 400 missile defense system from
the russians and that is something the
americans are not happy about so they
may sanction india as well
so
being a superpower is nice but it is
still a very very long wrong long road
ahead
for us
so that's where we are right now it's a
it's an interplay of multiple
uh of multiple domains
in geopolitics the global system the
global supply chains the economic
systems they got the financial
uh superstructure of the geopolitical
arena the military dimension is there
the various alliances are there very
complex so india right now is a small
economy three trillion three trillion
dollars yeah sure we are in the top five
top six in the world but that should not
be cause for celebration we have a long
road ahead of us
all right sir obey thank you very much
very good question nice meeting you
okay let's uh whom shall we bring in
let's bring in ronesh kumar
hello hi sir how are you
i'm very well sir how are you doing
where are you from
i'm from toronto canada so yeah as
always my sunday morning is starting
with your show yeah
oh very nice to meet you thank you so
much yes sir what's your question yes so
my question is uh currently india has
taken a neutral stand and i won't go in
the
that they should have taken it or not
because there are seem to be valid
argument on each side but unlike china
which are a self-reliant superpower so
india is very very far away from that
and uh so my question was so again this
thing is emerging then india needs to be
self-reliant
india needs to become as economic
superpower and that's not possible
without them becoming a manufacturing
superpower like china but in some of
your earlier shows you had hindered
towards that u.s had assisted china a
lot in that and the same as maybe japan
and south korea so my question is that
is india in a position that they can
become and manufacturing or on a larger
labor and economic superpower without
the best assistant assistance and
currently with their uh current stance
that they have taken
excellent question sir very good
question i'll answer it now thank you so
much nice meeting you again
this is a brilliant question
so the china the rise of china happened
it's a very very rapid and meteoric rise
they came from nowhere and became a
genuine
economic
large power almost a superpower you
could say
and this happened because the united
states aided and abetted the rise of
china they brought china
in the the into the global economic
system they integrated china into the
global economic system
they outsourced all of their
manufacturing requirements to china
and they became china's biggest market
that the chinese could sell to and
that's why the chinese were able to grow
at more than 10
per year for such a long time and that's
how they were able to grow their economy
so fast that so-called chinese miracle
was actually done by the us
and similarly the japanese economic
miracle also happened because japan was
integrated into the u.s economy japan is
obviously as we know as i hope you guys
know it is under u.s occupation even
today it's not really a sovereign
country so the japanese rose very fast
in the 1980s they became almost like a
financial economic superpower the number
two economy in the world
and then something strange happened in
the japanese economy suddenly became
stagnant somehow magically
as if somebody switched off a button and
the south koreans also grew very fast
because of american help and so on so
it's a very interesting observation that
rhonesh has done now that the challenge
for india is that india also wants to
rise like this but the americans are not
going to help us the way they helped the
chinese or the japanese or the south
koreans
the americans they see india as a big
market 1.3 billion people so it's a
market that they want to keep selling
things to they want india to be a nation
of consumers
not a nation of producers
they don't want to see another big
economic miracle that comes up and
becomes another another challenge to
them
so it's going to be
a very big challenge for india to rise
under these circumstances economically
if india wants to reach the 10 trillion
dollar mark in the next 10 15 20 years
it's gonna have to grow
at close to ten percent a year or more
than that for
at least a decade or if not more
and how do we do that manufacturing is
the way to go but who's gonna buy what
we manufacture there is a huge big world
out there but much of the world is what
we call the third world they don't have
that much
spending power so if you manufacture all
kinds of goods items etc
who's gonna buy it
so that's the challenge india faces
right now
and that's that's a very big challenge
so
i'm not sure i have the answer
see some things are very difficult some
some questions
are not easy to answer
so it's for the government to find ways
of doing it
right
so one of the ways is to is to uh
is to start creating infrastructure
which will give rise to jobs and all
that for instance when you had the
japanese tsunami in 2011 it led to a to
a reasonable boom in the economy because
so much destruction happened as a
consequence of the tsunami and a lot of
nation rebuilding had to be done so it
gave rise to lots of jobs and lots of
contracts you know civil engineering
contracts and all that so that is one
way of creating a boom so in india there
is no tsunami but the nation needs a lot
of infrastructure we have no
infrastructure we need roads railways
airports
ports we need a lot of all that so maybe
we could you do that
maybe we could use that as a way of
starting our
manufacturing output and there are other
things we can also do there are various
other countries that we can align with
not necessarily only the us of course if
the u.s is willing to help great
so there are solutions but the solutions
are not as straightforward as the one
that the chinese had that just sell to
the us and take away all the
manufacturing india is going to have to
use a different approach but i am sure
the solutions are out there
so ronesh has asked a very good question
it's a very valid question it's a
different kind of challenge that india
is facing
so good question sir and nice meeting
you again thank you thank you sir thank
you
yeah
all right uh let us bring in who has
been waiting let's bring in um
let's bring in rishabh
hello
uh yeah hello sir good morning
good good morning
so currently i'm in usa and i'm from
indore madhya pradesh
nice to meet you sir nice to meet you
what's the question uh so my question is
that
as ukraine has used like many indian
student as a hostages
so in future
like
india will ever take a revenge or
something like that to give answer that
the thing which was done by ukraine was
not ethical
and uh so like
and like china also funds the other news
outlets in other country so why why
don't india do such kind of funding at
least at a small level to spread their
propaganda and indian perspective to the
western world or
to the other places
okay all right sir very good question
nice to meet you thank you i'm gonna
answer it now
so the question is will india take
revenge on ukraine
the the the focus for india right now
should be on getting all of our citizens
out of ukraine and back to safety back
in india
the ukrainians as rishabh pointed out
are indeed
holding indian students as hostages
they are using them employing them as
human shields there's been a lot of
racism there's been a lot of brutality
even the bbc was forced to report that
that's how widespread it has been
so that is indeed the case what needs to
happen is right now don't think about
revenge this just get everybody out of
that country right
and then what what's going to happen is
once we have all the people out of the
country
in the next 10 days or so i expect that
the russian military objectives will be
achieved
and then ukraine as we know it
will essentially cease to exist
you will have a new government
the russians are going to install a
different government this they're going
to oust mr zielinski
and then the government which will be in
place there will be a pro-russia
and i suppose more pro-india government
so then what's the
the question of taking revenge doesn't
actually arise because then the
government is going to be pro india and
let's say india wants to take revenge
is india in a position
to go and take revenge i mean in what
form do we
exact this revenge do we send our army
there
it's not
feasible for india to send an
expeditionary force in our armed force
all the way
those thousands of kilometers excuse me
all the way to ukraine
right you need supply lines and all that
so it's it's not really
uh
practical to do that and india doesn't
control the global economy so you can't
even impose financial sanctions and all
that
as long as you are not a very big and
powerful country sometimes you have to
swallow these insults and just do the
best you can
to
to bring your citizens back to safety
so that's what i can say
all we have to do right now is ensure
that every last indian gets out of
ukraine safely and is brought back home
and then we will see what the russians
do
in ukraine they're going to install a
different government
and so that's how it's going to do
that's how it is going to proceed
okay rasha thank you for the question
nice meeting you again
uh let's bring in
akshith
hello hi sir hi sir hello
i am
from himachal pradesh and i am doing i
am in delhi currently
so i have a question that uh india has a
population of 140 billion
and uk has a population of 8 crores
but we have comparatively equal gdp
how is it possible sir
how
how 130 140
140 crore people can match eight crore
people are indians so dumb
are we so dumb people that we can match
uh we are uh
we are equivalent to uk
eight crore people are equal to 130
crore people
is government fudging the data
or is it the real data how we can know
that india's gdp is equal to uk
okay good question sir uh i'll answer it
now so akshith says i you uk not ukraine
i heard ukraine first so india's
gdp is more or less equal to the uk's
gdp
our gdp whatever it's around three
trillion dollars
and the uk gdp is the same and our
population is obviously 1.3 billion and
theirs is much much smaller than ours
so how do you calculate the gdp
economists have a variety of ways of
calculating your gross domain your gross
domestic
product per year
so i am not an economist so i cannot
give you the details of how it is done
but there is there is a proper
methodology of doing it so it's quite
transparent and i think
it's it's well known what india's gdp is
and the uk gdp is so the question is we
have such a huge population
their their population is so small so
how come the two nations have the same
gdp well if you look at history if you
look at historical data of the past 2000
years
historically india's gdp used to be more
than one third of the entire world's gdp
that's how big india's gdp was so what
happened
the uk came to india the english came to
india
and stole away all of our wealth and
treasure and everything they destroyed
india's economy india was
the world's first industrialized fully
industrialized civilization the british
destroyed all of india's indigenous
industries
they destroyed all of our our technology
we we were a very technologically
advanced nation and because of that we
were the world's largest economy more
than one third of the entire world's gdp
was india's right
and by the time so when the british came
to india india accounted for more than
the one-third of the whole world's gdp
by the time the british left in 1947
india accounted for less than two
percent of the world's gdp so you can
guess where all the money went and what
where all the productivity went
all of it was transferred to the uk it
was all stolen to the uk to the uk it is
estimated that the british stole
approximately 45 trillion dollars worth
of treasure and money and all that from
india they can never repay it and
because of that their economy grew so
much
and that's why it is the way it is today
they are enjoying the
they're enjoying the stolen wealth the
the wealth that they stole from india
and because they destroyed india's
economy that's why our economy is so
small today it is growing again now so
after 1947 india's economy could have
grown very fast
but what happened is that we had the
great srineru who imposed the nairobian
rate of growth he refused to kick-start
india's economy and so our economy
stagnated until the 1990s
now it is growing faster and that's what
we are seeing
so if you look at the per capita gdp if
you look at the gdp total gdp and divide
by the population then india is a very
low income nation
and the western countries are very high
income nations
i'm not sure what is the current uh per
capita gdp it must be less than two
thousand dollars per
it must be two less than two thousand
dollars in the case of the uk us it must
be more than fifty thousand dollars
in the case of china it's like around
ten thousand dollars roughly i don't
have the exact figures
so
the real uh level of prosperity of a
country is is measured measured in terms
of gdp per capita not total gdp total
gdp is good for india it's around three
trillion trillion dollars it's in the
top five or top top six in the world but
if you look at per capita gdp india is a
very poor country because the average
wealth per person is very very less
so it's because of what happened in the
last
000 years first we were occupied
by the turks then we were occupied by
the british and the british destroyed
india's economy thoroughly today we are
just rising from the dead
so that's why we are where we are today
it's not because the indian government
is incompetent or it is not doing its
job it's because of what happened in the
last 500 to 1000 years
so no matter how good your government is
it's going to take time for your gdp
graph to go higher and higher it's going
to take time it's going to take at least
10 20 years minimum for india to become
a 10 trillion dollar economy minimum 20
years 10 to 20 years so it's not the
government's fault this government right
now it is not their fault india's
economy is broken or it is the way it is
it's because of the what the foreign
occupiers did to india
all right so interesting question
akshith nice meeting you
okay let's bring in somebody else uh
let's bring in vishwanaths
or could you unmute yourself please i
can't hear you oh sorry yeah hello sir
from bangalore nice to talk to you nice
to meet you nice to meet you yeah uh
is is it the right time uh
for india to look into uh the chinese
occupied part of india or the pakistan
occupied part of india
okay very good very short brief question
thank you so much uh i'm going to answer
it is it the right time
for india to think about retaking
chinese occupied exciting
or pakistan occupied kashmir
so when is it the right time for any
nation to take back territory from a
different country which is currently
taken by the other country you can do it
when you know that if you take this
action there's going to be no adverse
consequences that you will have to face
right
so right now if you go and try to take
back
aksai chin
from the chinese
do you expect the chinese not to
retaliate in some way
they're going to retaliate they're a
much more powerful economy than ours and
they have a
better military strength than us
so there's going to be
a retaliation from the chinese
are we prepared
to absorb that retaliation are we
prepared to absorb the damage are we in
a position to go to war with china right
now
obviously we are not
so it is not the right time for india
to even think of taking back
aksai
the pakistanis are a client state of the
chinese
they have nuclear weapons
does india want to start a war with a
nuclear powered state right now is india
that powerful today
obviously india is not that powerful
today
india cannot think of starting a war
with anybody when india is trying to
grow its economy
we cannot
afford
to have any kind of damage to our
infrastructure to our country to our
economy only when india becomes a
genuine superpower
can we think of doing these things but
the thing about becoming a genuine
superpower is that you don't even have
to go to war
everybody wants to be your friend
that's how it works
so you can win your wars without firing
a single bullet if you grow your economy
and your military strength to a certain
extent
so right now we need to forget about pok
we need to forget about exciting we need
to forget about all of that we need to
focus on building our economy and our
military might
next 20 years just focus on building the
economy work very hard
and then you will find that magically
all the problems will go away
so the solution to all the problems for
india right now is to focus on building
up our economic strength because as your
economy grows you can spend more on your
military as well
so all the problems they have the same
solution build your economy focus on
building up the economy
that's what we need to do right now
forget about p okay forget about
extension for the next 20 years there
will be a time for all of that but the
time is not now
all right
so a good question
and let's bring in somebody
else
so viswana thank you very much good
question
okay
whom shall i bring in let's bring in um
shreyas
hello
i am from mumbai
nice to meet you sir
my question to you is that if china
invades taiwan and we secure sri lanka
then the chinese debt that is in sri
lanka will that be cancelled off or
china will go
and take international
maybe protest against us that oh we have
invested so much in china and india has
already secured
that is my question
okay very good question first thank you
and let me answer that
so if the chinese invade taiwan
and india secure sri lanka so the
question is like i use the word secure
and people don't really know what it
means
by secure i mean make sure that the
chinese cannot come and interfere there
that's what i mean i don't mean that we
should go and invade and annex the
country same goes with nepal i said
india should secure nepal and ensure
that nepal's territorial integrity and
sovereignty is safeguarded that's what i
mean
so uh
but what uh shreya says said just now is
of course quite quite interesting and
important because the chinese have
trapped sri lanka in their infamous debt
trap
and the sri lankans
took a chinese loan
at ridiculous interest rates
and now they're unable to repay it
and that's why the chinese are not
grabbing sri lankan territory they've
taken over possession of the shield of
the port that the sri lankans have built
and this is the the way the chinese
expand their uh
their territorial footprint and
strategic footprint in various countries
so
so one thing india can do
is give the money to sri lanka to pay
off the chinese debt that way the sri
lankans are
free of the chinese but there has to be
strings attached you can't just get the
money for free you have to give us
something in return so maybe india can
invest in the port or do something like
that so india needs to find creative
ways of extricating sri lanka from the
from the trap they have
fallen into
and the question is how do the chinese
get countries
to fall into these dead traps they do it
by bribes
they bribe whoever is the politician
who's running the country give them a
few million dollars maybe
maybe more than a few million dollars
and get them to sign on the contract
that traps the country
into the ridiculous uh
interest rate that cannot be repaid
so that's how they do it so if the
chinese invade taiwan so the thing is
this
i don't expect the chinese
to be in a position to invade taiwan
right now like i said just now there is
a time and a place for everything right
now india cannot think of taking
uh aksai chin or pakistan but kashmir
because the time is not right
india has the other priorities similarly
i don't think the time is right for the
chinese to make a move on taiwan because
taiwan is a red line for the americans
the americans simply cannot afford to
allow the chinese to take taiwan because
then the the entire supremacy hegemony
that the americans have built up will be
broken nobody will trust the americans
anymore the americans will no longer be
the guarantors of safety in the world
they will not be able to dictate the
rules that the world must follow if the
chinese succeed in capturing taiwan
american hegemony is broken america is
no longer a superpower america is
humiliated so the americans will not
allow this to happen
if the chinese make a move on taiwan
there's going to be a very very
significant retaliation and the chinese
know that
that's why the chinese will not try to
take that one right now they will wait
for a few more years in the in the
meanwhile they may try to make a move on
india so these these are the things that
are happening right now we need to be
prepared for that
so uh i don't expect a chinese move on
taiwan right now it is more likely that
they may make a move on india and try to
create some mischief so that's where we
are so shreyas thank you very much good
question nice meeting you
okay let's bring in girish
hello
hello sir hello
yes hi where are you from
hello
i am from lunar
lunar
um
okay
okay what's your question um
my question is
india china russia and other
asian countries can make their own
treaty organization just like natto
to counter western countries
good question
good question girish okay let me answer
that
so can india
russia china and various other asian
countries
form their own alliance to counter nato
or the u.s hegemony it's a very
interesting question
there is certainly going to be a
temptation among asian countries to make
their own to form their own coalition
their own bloc their own
alliance
which could possibly uh offset the us
hegemony in the world right now what we
are seeing is that people the various
countries are now
kind of getting fed up of u.s hegemony
the americans have been dictating
how people should behave what people
should do what people should not do for
a very long time
and now the russians have pushed back
they have shown the world that the
americans were unable to
protect ukraine the americans made some
promises but then they did not keep it
they essentially abandoned ukraine
and they have imposed
a whole bucket load of sanctions on the
russians
so what they have done is that
they they have
they have put mr putin in a position
where he has nothing more to lose
how many more sanctions can they throw
at him they've already already thrown
the whole kitchen sink at him so now
they what they have done is they have
pushed russia
and china
together
the russians and chinese can now be
looked upon as almost like an alliance
and if they really want to reshape the
world order
they will need one more large powerful
country
the two of them are not enough to
reshape the world order what they really
seek to do
is to make a new world order or to
bipolarize the world right now the world
is a unipolar world the entire world is
run by one system
the the global system which is
essentially controlled by the americans
all the financial institutions are
theirs the reserve currency is theirs
and so on and so forth
the so what the chinese and the russians
want to do is they want to create a
parallel system
but these two countries are not enough
so they may want
possibly
india to become part of that parallel
system but it's not possible when india
and china have such an adversarial
relationship such an antagonistic
relationship
so we don't know
if
there's a resolution to this
if the chinese really want india to come
into that fold
then they may have to give some big
incentives to india
because obviously the americans won't
like it and then america will
will put imposed sanctions on india as
well
so
so right now we don't have answers to
these questions we don't know what's
going to happen what these leaders are
planning what india is planning what the
chinese are planning what are we
forecasting from the indian side
what way is the world going to move
towards so right now everything is up in
the air we don't quite know it all
depends on the next five moves the
chinese made make the next five moves
the americans make what direction russia
takes and what choices india also will
make so all of these things will
determine the way the world is going to
move towards in the next
few years i expect that in the next few
years you're gonna see a lot of chaos
it's gonna be a very interesting time
so that's what i can say we don't have
any definitive answers yet but it is
certainly a possibility that you may
eventually see the emergence of an
eastern bloc of nations india china
russia and various other smaller
countries it is possible
depending on how things are taken
forward
so good question girish
okay
let's bring in
whom shall i bring in
girish
hello
hello sir
um my name is
hi
i'm calling from stuttgart i'm uh
stuart guard stuart guard stuttgart
germany yes yes
so i'm a fan of your ideas i'm a fan of
your work i'm
it's incredible you're answering so
questions eloquently so my question is
in the india's political history this is
the best time considering
the absolute majority it has to take any
decision
but
but if you see on the ground
it is very
relatively easy to influence neighboring
nations like
sri lanka bangladesh and nepal by
they are all smaller economies so sri
lanka is struggling to pay off its
relatively small debt of 3 billion
dollars and india's is 3 trillion nearly
so
why it is not doing to influence these
countries these are smaller economies
and you can deal with all
say
20 30 billion
that is one
and second one is
of course india's economy should
uh related to that
okay one question one question
okay so
related to these countries
also our
our
reserve on the
military expenditure is also going down
year after year if you compare to the
gdp
so this is a kind of contrary to what we
want to be
with the best majority and
it
it's really scary if the majority is not
there if there is a khiri government
then it's going to be even more
difficult yeah that's my question
okay thank you so much for the question
let me answer that nice meeting you
again
so uh
yeah india has the indian government
which is currently in power has a
absolute majority in parliament which
means that theoretically they should be
able to do whatever they want now like
girish mentioned a country like sri
lanka is right now trapped in the debt
trap of china they're not able to repay
the loan which is like he said about
three billion dollars i don't have the
exact statistics but let's say what he
is saying is correct
so india could help sri lanka out and
extricate it from the difficult position
it is in the question is what does india
get in return there are no free lunches
in the world in geopolitics you do
everything for a certain purpose when
you put a certain amount of money in a
certain thing
you expect something back there are no
free gifts no free lunches
and the problem is that
we are not the only country that is in a
position to influence let's say sri
lanka or bangladesh
lots of other powerful countries are
vying for the same influence in our
region in the indian subcontinental
region for instance the chinese have
deeper pockets than india if they want
they can influence bangladesh to a
greater degree than india
the americans also have deeper pockets
and they can also influence these
countries and many of these countries
that i just mentioned don't really want
india's influence to grow
so india is currently not currently
india has always been in this
magnificent position in the indian ocean
region india dominates the entire region
and yet india
as of today doesn't is not in a position
to exert any
strategic influence far beyond its
shores
so that's not because india is not
powerful enough for india is not trying
to do so but because there are more
powerful countries that are already in
control
of these of these
things that we are not able to quite see
right now so uh
despite having a brute majority in
parliament
the thing is that
power doesn't
you don't understand what power is
power doesn't arise from the number of
votes you get or the number of seats you
in parliament
power is a whole different thing there
are extra governmental
extra democratic power structures that
exist in the world in every country
that
are not quite visible to us right
so power depends on how many
levels
or in the country you can control and
there are lots of things that you can
control without ever having a single
state in parliament so it's like that so
so just because you have a majority in
parliament doesn't mean that you can do
everything for instance the indian
federal structure is that you the
central government cannot tell states
what to do
even if it it will sign an agreement
with the diff with a certain country to
have let's say a bullet train system
from point a to point b let's say from
north india to south india if the
various states in the way refuse to
cooperate then the entire project is
never going to take off and then you
have the judiciary that has that things
to that sings its own tune and so on so
there are so many things that prevent
the central government from
doing things that it wants to do and
power is not influence the influence is
not power
i would not agree with that so you know
it's like that see
what is influence and what is power
there is a very significant difference
let's say you are a celebrity and you
have 10 million followers on instagram
and these people 10 million people they
will listen to what you say because
they're interested in what you have to
say that is called influence
now let's consider another scenario
you have
well-trained
heavily armed men at your disposal who
will immediately obey you without
question
that is power
the other thing is influence power is
more valuable so that is the situation
that we are in today
democracy is kind of overrated it
doesn't give you the power that you need
to the extent that we believe it is
all right sir so thank you for the
question nice meeting you girish
okay let us bring in abhishek
hello
namaste
all right sir what's your question
sir can you tell me about how u.s is
losing its hm money over around the
globe and how is it a declining position
yes good question abhishek thank you uh
let me answer the question
so the u.s
hegemony is being lost because it is
losing
it's a good question how did this happen
so
power and leadership
are closely interrelated when you have
good leaders you gotta be powerful
when you have leaders who lack vision or
who are not vigorous or who are a little
bit feeble so to say
then you will lose power and if you have
a succession of such leaders who are
good at talking but not good good at
taking action then your country over
time
will lose its power now what is the
power the u.s is losing first of all the
chinese influence is rising when you
have a very big economy you're going to
have a correspondingly bigger footprint
in terms of power projection your
military will be will be larger you will
be able to control the global systems
and all that so that is what has given
rise to american power firstly
they are the largest economy in the
world they control the economic
systems of the world the supply chains
uh the global uh institutions economic
institutions like the world bank the imf
etc their currency is the global reserve
currency
so that these are the manifestations of
american power and control over the
world now the chinese influence is
rising
they have infiltrated the united united
nations the who their currency is
gaining in strength lots of countries
are accepting the chinese currency
uh in in
economic transactions so that is causing
the american power to get to become
weaker then they had a military presence
all across the world now they have
abdicated it to some extent in eurasia
they have
evacuated from afghanistan they no
longer have a position presence there
they no longer have a presence in
central asia like they used to have
and so on so you can see the visible
decline
their geographical footprint is
declining
their economic power is declining the
chinese power is rising chinese economy
is rising the chinese military strength
is also rising the naval strength is
rising the american strength is the same
so if you look at the comparative
trajectory of the graph the chinese
graph is rising the american graph is
stagnating
so that's how we know
that overall american influence and
power in the world is waning and as you
can see if you look at american society
american society is in chaos there is so
much division and strife in american
society today the so-called american
exceptionalism is not to be seen
anywhere it has been replaced by this
mediocrity the vocal culture so america
is not producing great leaders anymore
so overall the country is visibly in
decline so that's why people all over
the world are saying that american power
is declining now
okay abhishek so that's what i can say
good question nice meeting you
okay who else is waiting lots of people
are waiting let's bring in kanav
hello good evening sir good evening
good evening sir where are you from
sir i'm from himachal pradesh
nice to meet you sir what's your
question so my question is that uh
coming back to the russia ukraine
conflict my question is that what u.s
exactly wants like us is expanding its
nato despite the fact that for what it
was made back in 1949 it has already
expired so i want to know that why is
u.s continuing the uh the dead cold war
till now what's the main motto of it is
that does the u.s want to make a
lucrative market of it is u.s making
money out of it or there is something
else else reason related to it i want to
know that what u.s exactly wants in nato
perspective
very good question very good question
short and and brief and precise good let
me answer that
so what is the objective of nato and
what does the us want very good question
that goes to the heart of the entire
matter
the us has always wanted global hegemony
world domination there should be no
power on the planet that can challenge
the united states they don't they will
not tolerate a large nation or a
powerful nation anywhere in the world as
far as they can if they can they will
destroy all countries that is what's
known as this is the secretive blitzer
doctrine
okay so that's what it is so they will
they even after the ussr broke up we
still had this very big country called
russia
right
so for some time they were able to
influence russia there was this guy
called boris yeltsin who was essentially
a u.s agent and what boris yeltsin did
was he systematically and deliberately
destroyed the russian economy
so in when the ussr was in place
it was a collectivized society it was a
communist country
which means that all the property all
the wealth
was collectivized and it was
it was uh
it was in the custody of the government
the wealth belonged to the people to the
nation but its custodian was the
government and the government would
decide what it would be used for
so all that wealth belonged to the
people and it was in the custody of the
of the ussr's government after the ussr
broke up and the russian government came
to power
under boris yeltsin what he did
was it
he took all this money
and he gave it away as gifts to various
oligarchs these so-called businessmen
who
who were in his favor
so all of this money that belonged to
the people
of russia he gave it away as gifts to a
number of
businessmen oligarchs and that's what
gave rise to this very powerful
oligarchs that we have in russia today
so all the wealth was stolen and then
what these oligarchs did
was they were given the task of
running businesses that would fail
so all of the wealth of the ussr was
frittered away and the russian
economy went into a shambles there was
very high inflation and russia became
almost like a failed country
until
vladimir putin came into the picture and
then he arrested the fall and then
slowly over time over the last 20 years
he has kind of rebuilt the economy to a
certain extent
and russia is reasonably stable today
so boris yeltsin was essentially a us
agent he presided over the destruction
of the russian economy before him you
had mikhail gorbachev who broke the ussr
itself so the u.s
even after the ussr broke up wanted to
further destroy russia
and that was the purpose of nato after
the dissolution of the ussr so nato was
built was created as a counterweight to
the ussr after the ussr broke up
nato started expanding eastwards by even
though the promise was made it would not
do so
and its aim was to encircle russia and
prevent russia from exerting any kind of
geopolitical influence
in the countries it used to
have influence over in the past so the
overall objective
was to destroy the strength of the of
the russian nation
and to
to uh ensure that it is never a threat
in the future to the us so that was the
objective and that's always been the
objective of
the world over
when it comes to u.s foreign policy and
the same goes for india they don't want
india to rise they did not want china to
rise they made a very very big mistake
in uh they miscalculated what the
chinese would be like they thought they
would be able to influence china once
china was integrated into the global
economy into the u.s led global economy
once china became a capitalist country
they assumed that china would again
become democratic also which never
happened so they made a huge blunder
there
so that's how it has been so the
objective of nato is to has been to
destroy the ussr first and then russia
but
now it has it has reached a very big
roadblock
all right
so that's the answer sir very good
question
and thank you for the question nice
meeting you
okay let us bring in um
urmil
hello hello hello sir
hi nice to meet you sir where are you
from
so i'm in the u.s right now
okay what's your question sir
so like you predicted and uh some of
your guests in your podcast predicted
that india is facing an imminent threat
from china in near future
so how does india need to prepare it in
terms of diplomatic perspective or
should we go in terms of military
perspectives saying looking keeping in
mind that we won't get enough support
from maybe russia and us as of now
with our stand with which we have in
terms of the current crisis
good question sir let me answer that now
so uh yes
it is believed it is it is being
anticipated that india and china may
may be engaged in some kind of conflict
in the in the forthcoming
future definitely before 2024 that is
what is being expected so what does
india need to do to prepare for this is
there a diplomatic solution when
somebody attacks you militarily there is
no diplomatic solution
if the conflict happens it will not be
started by india because india is does
not want to have any kind of military
conflict india is right now it's only
ambition is to grow its economy so when
you're trying to grow your your economy
you know you don't want to enter into
any kind of military conflict with
anybody so if a conflict with china
happens it's going to be started
initiated by the chinese or military
conflict
and as you rightly said nobody is going
to come and help india not the us
the us doesn't want to help india and
the russians are not in a position to
help india because they need the chinese
on their side so if a conflict happens
india is on its own so what does india
need to do to prepare for this india
needs to be aware that something like
this can happen india needs to ensure it
has the right amount of missiles
cruise missiles ready brahmos missiles
hopefully the other one the other cruise
missile which we have what's it called
nearby i think
and india needs to
keep an eye on the chinese deployments
in chinese occupied tibet
we should we have satellites and all
that so we know what's happening
so we need to monitor this on a
day-to-day hour to our basis to know
what the chinese are up to of course
it's not as easy as i make it sound
right now things are difficult because
the terrain is very mountainous it's the
himalayas but we need to be prepared we
need to know how many fighter planes are
deployed deployed in tibet how many
chinese fighter planes are there what
are the movements and so on so forth so
if something happens we will be aware of
it we should be able to anticipate that
something is happening something is
coming right now
our military strength is reasonably good
and of course we have
the brahmastra
which tells the chinese that you there
is a certain line you simply cannot
cross
and if you cross that you're gonna pay
the price for it so we have that
so the chinese objective is not going to
be to come and invade india and occupy
india it will be to humiliate india that
will be their limited objective so for
instance by
taking a big bite out of indian
territory maybe in the northeast or
maybe by cutting off the northeast of
the chicken's neck these may be the
objectives and they would be hoping that
if
india is humiliated like that then in
the next elections the government will
fall and a more
and a government that like will come to
power so that could be the objective so
india needs to be prepared our military
strength is reasonably good i don't
think the chinese if we are well
prepared then i don't think they think
the chinese will be able to succeed in
such a misadventure they may actually
have to pay a big price for that
so india needs to
be aware
simply that such a thing can happen in
the forthcoming days and india needs to
keep monitoring the situation in china's
occupied tibet day by day hour by hour
and then we will be in a good position
to deal with this
but one thing we should be aware of is
that nobody is going to come and help us
so we will have to take this on our own
all right
thank you for the question nice meeting
you thank you
yeah
okay let's take a couple more questions
let's bring in shazin
hello
can i be heard hi
yes i can hear you ma'am where are you
from i'm um i'm originally from
bangladesh but i live in canada
um
nice to meet you too
um so i've been um i've been following
you for the last like half a year or so
that's how i was introduced to you so
i'm
if i'm just super knowledgeable and very
like informative when it comes to like
geopolitics
um so
my question is is that um
if let's say if india and china were to
get into like a ruffle or or some sort
of like conflict
um
where do you think like uh
countries like bangladesh and sri lanka
like smaller countries within within the
sarc federation
where do you think that they would stand
and how do you think
they would prepare for that type of uh
invasion or conflict
good question i'm going to answer it now
thank you nice meeting you
yes so if india and china enter into a
military conflict what will be the
position or the role of countries like
bangladesh sri lanka maybe pakistan etc
so let's not let's not talk about
pakistan bangladesh and sri lanka these
are countries that are very much part of
the indian ocean and indian subcontinent
region
i would expect that bangladesh and sri
lanka would try and be neutral as far as
possible in such a conflict because they
don't want to get involved in this and
dragged into this
and there is no need for bangladesh or
sri lanka to get involved in this
if there is a conflict between india and
china a short war or something it is
definitely going to be initiated by
china
and they will try and
their objective will be to take a bite
out of indian territory maybe cut off
the northeast north eastern part of
india and try to humiliate india and
ensure that the government falls in the
next election so that's going to be the
limited objective and then when when a
different government comes to power once
one that is a weaker government maybe a
coalition government more pliable for
china then they will try to drag india
into their chinese financial and
geopolitical orbit so that would be the
big picture objective of the chinese if
they were to initiate a military
conflict with india it will be a short
sharp
war not a long protracted war
in such a case i don't expect
a country like bangladesh or a country
like srilanka to even get involved in
any way at all if it's a week-long or
two-week
long conflict there's no need for
these countries to get involved and it
would be best for a country like
bangladesh or sri lanka to stay out of
this
because
when two elephants or giants are
fighting a smaller animal doesn't want
to be part of that so i don't expect
bangladesh or sri lanka to get to
to be involved to any extent in this
on the other hand if the chinese
capture taiwan
then countries like sri lanka and
bangladesh may become targets or they
may be rude by the chinese because the
chinese have this policy called the
string of pearls policy of encircling
india at sea
if they become if they succeed in taking
taiwan then they'll become major power
in the indo-pacific region and then
countries like sri lanka and bangladesh
would be very happy
to offer their services ports and
facilities to china so as to stay on the
good side of china so in case the
chinese take to take taiwan then the
situation changes but if it's a conflict
between china and india
most likely sri lanka and bangladesh
will stay neutral and stay out of it so
that's how i see it going if this
happens so shazeen very good question
and nice meeting you
okay let's take maybe one or two more
questions uh
let's bring in mr
rishikesh rishikesh
[Music]
a month ago
i asked a question back then too yeah i
kind of remember you yes right
glad you could
yeah so
currently we are aware that um the asia
pacific is a hot spot for you know
initiation of a global conflict in the
long run and
navy will have a significant part in it
but i remember that
you once clarified that the japanese
navy
possesses like more strength than the
indian navy
and they are a more significant threat
to the chinese than the indians should
be because we are their you know direct
director opponents right now
so how come japanese navy possess more
threat to the chinese than the indian
navy while we have a larger budget and
more people in our country
good questions a good question yeah let
me answer that
so like rishikesh said the japanese navy
is more powerful than than the indian
navy it is more potent and why is it so
so firstly how do you determine the
strength
of a navy
typically most people would imagine is
that what most people would imagine is
that if you have more ships you are a
more powerful navy but that is not the
case
the actual strength of a navy is
determined by the number of of anti-ship
missiles you can deploy
at sea on a given day
so the japanese i believe they can
deploy on any given day approximately 1
500 anti-ship missiles offensive
missiles
that's a whole lot of missiles
uh
india cannot deploy anything like that
number of missiles so that's why the
japanese navy is way more powerful than
the indian navy and secondly
their submarines are some of the best
submarines in the world
very
very uh
very good technology very silent
submarines and very powerful submarine
in terms of offensive ability even the
submarines they have retired are better
than the submarines we have right now
right so so it's so why is it like this
or such a small country has a better
navy than us because they are any almost
like an economics overpower their naval
budget is greater than india's naval
budget and their technology is far
superior than any technology we have
developed in the
past decades because essentially we have
not been developing any technology at
all we are simply being purchased
purchasing
weapons
from other countries whether it's
submarines whether it is
anything else air force whatever
so that is why the japanese navy is way
more advanced and way more
technologically advanced and way more
powerful than the indian navy and also
because they have they are able to
deploy way more missiles than us so it's
about offensive missiles it's not about
defensive missiles there are certain
missiles that that are anti-missile
missiles
like the barak 8 missile that india has
so that's how it is so the japanese have
more they have better warships they have
more warships i believe
and they they have better submarines and
overall they just have a better navy and
their naval budget is greater than
india's naval budget as far as i know i
haven't uh compared the figures recently
but they they're a huge economy right so
so that's the reason why it is the way
it is all right so i hope i answer the
question rishikesh very interesting
question nice meeting you sir thank you
bye
okay let us take
let's take one more question uh
okay future leader or something
okay
hello sir okay hello
good evening uh sam from exactly good
evening
delhi all
right uh so so my question is that uh
isn't uh zelinski using its citizen as
uh hostages since he said
that
people between the age of 18 to 60 can't
leave ukraine and and using petroitism
and media
uh to show them as uh
on the good side but actually he's
holding holding them as hostages and
since russian forces will be forced to
kill the armed civilians and then they
will use this propaganda against asia
that see they are killing a civilian
station for killing civilians over here
yes sir good question uh let me answer
that so like you said you're right the
they are certainly using foreign
nationals as human shields as hostages
they are holding indians and africans
and various
people from other nationalities mainly
students but also like you said they are
trying to forcibly conscript civilians
into the armed forces
uh there are videos circulating on
social media of the
various battalions paramilitary
parliament military forces militias
stopping cars on the streets dragging
people out and forcing them to to
join the the conflict giving weapons and
all that
so yes this is extremely unethical and
if you if you put ak-47s and automatic
rifles in there in the hands of
civilians
then the opposition force the russians
will be compelled to treat those people
as enemy combatants and that's going to
create unnecessary completely
completely avoidable civilian casualties
so that's a very cynical and diabolical
approach
the zelinski government has taken
maybe they are being told to do so from
by their masters living another sitting
in another country
maybe that's that's the case and this
all goes into the propaganda warfare the
more civilian debts you have the worst
the russians look so it's all about
making the russians look bad
that's just terrible because you are
using humans as cannon fodder innocent
civilians but that's indeed what's
happening and it's it's very very sad i
mean war is tragic as it is and if you
get civilians involved in that it's even
worse
so yes that is unfortunately what's
happening but that's the the nature of
warfare you have all kinds of avoidable
and pointless
atrocities and deaths and loss of life
and it's the civilians always the
innocent civilians who suffer the most
anyhow yeah that's a good question thank
you for the question sir
okay let's let's bring in one final
person anubhab
hello
hello sir
i'm from i say i'm from kolkata
and my question is is there any player
or any warmonger who is trying to stress
the word more
is there anybody who is trying to
stretch the more the war more make it
yes sir oh
okay okay got the question thank you for
the question
is there any person who is trying to
lengthen the war uh yes i i think it is
the ukrainian government which is trying
to delay the
russian advance by putting civilians
where they should not be
when the
russians are advancing if you put
civilians in the military installations
as a human shields then the russians
will be forced to slow down the progress
because they they have been told to
ensure there are as few civilian
casualties as possible
and again the russians
are under instructions to ensure there
are no indian debts as far as possible
and if the zarenski government is
putting indians in harm's way holding
them hostages
and putting them uh and forcing them to
be in military installations then the
russians will have to be extremely
careful not to
cause deaths of indians so yes these are
ways in which you can delay the progress
of the war
and
make sure there are more civilian
casualties and make the other side look
bad
so yes that's indeed what's happening
right so
yeah that's the answer thank you
honorable nice meeting you
uh
should i take one more question
okay let me take one more question by
shashank
hello
hello sir how are you
i am very well sir how are you doing
where i am from yes sir i'm from
hyderabad sir
nice to meet you it's been a great
pleasure meeting you
uh but actually i have a doubt
that
he's putting trying to reunion like he's
trying to reunite the soviet union by
invading one one country after the other
like he started with ukraine now here
can he go with other countries the
remaining 15 countries for his
fatherland
some like nazi ideology
what putin actually wants
yes
okay good question sir so
one country after another has not
happened he is going for ukraine right
now
and the reason for that is because
ukraine was trying to join nato and that
would be a red line that he cannot allow
them to cross because then you will have
the american forces and nato forces
forces right on his doorstep so that is
the reason why he did that
he is not in a position to go and start
invading country after country he is not
in that position he's not a madman
so even if he may be harboring ambitions
of recreating the ussr we don't know
what's going on in mr putin's head
we are not privy to his private personal
thoughts so we don't know
but uh he is not crazy he is a very
rational person
so he is simply trying to effect a
regime change in ukraine he may not even
try to take over the entire country he
may leave one third of the country out
of his
dominion
by the time the invasion is completed so
that's what we can see right now as far
as what is going on in his mind does he
plan to invade one country after another
i don't think so he is not crazy like
adolf hitler was he is not
mad and that greedy and he knows what
his limitations are
he is under incredible sanctions right
now and he has to do
i mean he he has to ensure that he is
not going on the bad side of china if he
starts acting like adolf hitler then the
chinese will not be in a position to
support him anymore
so there is a delicate balancing game
that's being played
and all he is trying to do is to
counterbalance nato and ensure that nato
doesn't
move eastwards any further because that
would be a mortal deadly threat to his
country so that is what he is doing i do
not think he's going to start invading
country after country and even if he
wants to he is not in a position to do
that and the chinese will not
support
such
an action
all right so that's the answer
and that brings us to the end of today's
session i know there are lots of people
waiting i apologize to all of you
who have entered but
this is the end of today's session thank
you so much for to everybody for your
questions thank you for all the viewers
on all the support
and let's keep doing this so
i will see you all
in the next episode thank you very much
take care